<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book id="oprofile-guide">
<bookinfo>
	<title>OProfile manual</title>

	<authorgroup>
		<author>
			<firstname>John</firstname>
			<surname>Levon</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address><email>levon@movementarian.org</email></address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</authorgroup>

	<copyright>
		<year>2000-2004</year>
		<holder>Victoria University of Manchester, John Levon and others</holder>
	</copyright>
</bookinfo>

<toc></toc>

<chapter id="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
This manual applies to OProfile version <oprofileversion />.
OProfile is a set of performance monitoring tools for Linux 2.6 and higher systems, available on a number of architectures.
OProfile provides the following features:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Profiler</listitem>
<listitem>Post-processing tools for analyzing profile data</listitem>
<listitem>Event counter</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
OProfile is capable of monitoring native hardware events occurring in all parts of a running system, from the kernel
(including modules and interrupt handlers) to shared libraries
to binaries. OProfile can collect event information for the whole system in the background with very little overhead. These
features make it ideal for monitoring entire systems to determine bottle necks in real-world systems.
</para>

<para>
Many CPUs provide "performance counters", hardware registers that can count "events"; for example,
cache misses, or CPU cycles. OProfile can collect profiles of code based on the number of these occurring events:
repeatedly, every time a certain (configurable) number of events has occurred, the PC value is recorded.
This information is aggregated into profiles for each binary image.  Alternatively, OProfile's event counting
tool can collect simple raw event counts.</para>
<sect1 id="legacy_mode">
<title>OProfile legacy profiling mode</title>
Prior to release 1.0, OProfile included a profiling tool consisting of the <command>opcontrol</command> shell script, the <command>oprofiled</command> daemon,
and the attendant oprofile kernel driver. This "legacy profiler" was deprecated in release 0.9.8 with the introduction of
the <command>operf</command> profiling tool (see <xref linkend="perf_events"/>). Some older architectures/platforms
do not support the use of <command>operf</command>. For those cases, oprofile users should install release 0.9.9, which is the
last release to include the legacy profiler.
</sect1>
<sect1 id="perf_events">
<title>OProfile perf_events profiling mode</title>
<para>
OProfile has the ability to profile a single process or every currently running process (i.e., system-wide)
via the <command>operf</command> program. <command>operf</command> interfaces with the
kernel to collect samples via the Linux Kernel Performance Events Subsystem (hereafter
referred to as "perf_events").  OProfile can co-exist with other tools on your system that
may also be using the perf_events kernel subsystem.
</para>
<para>
Using <command>operf</command> to profile a single
process can be done as a normal user; however, root authority <emphasis>is</emphasis> required to run
<command>operf</command> in system-wide profiling mode.
<note>
<title>Note</title>
Some older processor models are not supported by the underlying perf_events kernel and, thus, are not supported by <command>operf</command>.
If you receive the message
<screen>  Your kernel's Performance Events Subsystem does not support your processor type</screen>
when attempting to use <command>operf</command>, install OProfile 0.9.9 and try profiling with <command>opcontrol</command>
to see if your processor type may be supported by OProfile's legacy mode.
</note>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="event_counting">
<title>OProfile event counting mode</title>
OProfile provides the <command>ocount</command> tool for
collecting raw event counts on a per-application, per-process, per-cpu, or system-wide basis.  Unlike the
profiling tools, post-processing of the data collected is not necessary -- the data is displayed in the
output of <command>ocount</command>.  A common use case for event counting tools is when performance analysts
want to determine the CPI (cycles per instruction) for an application. High CPI implies possible stalls,
and many architectures provide events that give detailed information about the different types of stalls.
The events provided are architecture-specific, so we refer the reader to the hardware manuals available for
the processor type being used.
</sect1>


<sect1 id="applications">
<title>Applications of OProfile</title>
<para>
OProfile is useful in a number of situations. You might want to use OProfile when you :
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>need low overhead</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>cannot use highly intrusive profiling methods</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need to profile interrupt handlers</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need to profile an application and its shared libraries</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need to profile dynamically compiled code of supported virtual machines (see <xref linkend="jitsupport"/>)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need to capture the performance behaviour of entire system</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>want to examine hardware effects such as cache misses</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>want detailed source annotation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>want instruction-level profiles</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>want call-graph profiles</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
OProfile is not a panacea. OProfile might not be a complete solution when you :
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>require call graph profiles on platforms other than x86, ARM, and PowerPC</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>require 100% instruction-accurate profiles</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need function call counts or an interstitial profiling API</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>cannot tolerate any disturbance to the system whatsoever</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>need to profile interpreted or dynamically compiled code of non-supported virtual machines</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<sect2 id="jitsupport">
<title>Support for dynamically compiled (JIT) code</title>
<para>
OProfile provides a framework to support JITed code ("just-in-time (JIT) compiled code").
A development library is provided to allow developers
to add support for any VM (virtual machine) that produces dynamically compiled code (see the <emphasis>OProfile JIT agent
developer guide</emphasis>).
In addition, built-in support is included for the following:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem>JVMTI agent library for Java (1.5 and higher)</listitem>
<listitem>JVMPI agent library for Java (1.5 and lower)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
These libraries make it possible for OProfile to attribute profile samples
to Java methods. Without a VM-specific agent library, OProfile will typically report
samples from JITed code similar to the following example:
<screen>     anon: &lt;tgid&gt;&lt;address range&gt;</screen>
For information on how to use OProfile's JIT support, see <xref linkend="setup-jit"/>.
</sect2>

<sect2 id="guestsupport">
<title>No support for virtual machine guests</title>
<para>
OProfile currently does not support event-based profiling (i.e, using hardware events like cache misses,
branch mispredicts) on virtual machine guests running under systems such as VMware.
(Note: KVM guests <emphasis>are</emphasis> supported.)  The list of
supported events displayed by ophelp is based on CPU type and does
not take into account whether the running system is a guest system or real system.  To use
OProfile on such guest systems, you must use the legacy profiler's timer mode (see <xref linkend="timer" />).
</para>
</sect2>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="requirements">
<title>System requirements</title>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Linux kernel</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Release 2.6.31 or higher
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Supported architectures</term>
		<listitem><para>
			AMD, ARM, Intel, PowerPC, Tile, MIPS
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Required libraries</term>
		<listitem><para>
			These libraries are required : <filename>popt</filename>, <filename>bfd</filename>,
			<filename>liberty</filename> (debian users: libiberty is provided in binutils-dev package), <filename>dl</filename>,
			plus the standard C++ libraries.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Required kernel headers</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Either the kernel-headers package must be installed or use the <code>--with-kernel</code>
			configure option.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Required user account</term>
		<listitem><para>
			For secure processing of sample data from JIT virtual machines (e.g., Java),
			the special user account "oprofile" must exist on the system.  The 'configure'
			and 'make install' operations will print warning messages if this
			account is not found.  If you intend to profile JITed code, you must create
			a group account named 'oprofile' and then create the 'oprofile' user account,
			setting the default group to 'oprofile'.  A runtime error message is printed to
			the oprofile log when processing JIT samples if this special user
			account cannot be found.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
 		<term><acronym>ELF</acronym></term>
		<listitem><para>
			Probably not too strenuous a requirement, but older <acronym>A.OUT</acronym> binaries/libraries are not supported.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>K&amp;R coding style</term>
		<listitem><para>
			OK, so it's not really a requirement, but I wish it was...
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>


</sect1>

<sect1 id="resources">
<title>Internet resources</title>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Web page</term>
		<listitem><para>
			There is a web page (which you may be reading now) at
			<ulink url="http://oprofile.sf.net/">http://oprofile.sf.net/</ulink>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Download</term>
		<listitem><para>
			You can download a source tarball or check out code from
			the code repository at the sourceforge page,
			<ulink url="http://sf.net/projects/oprofile/">http://sf.net/projects/oprofile/</ulink>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Mailing list</term>
		<listitem><para>
			There is a low-traffic OProfile-specific mailing list, details at
			<ulink url="http://sf.net/mail/?group_id=16191">http://sf.net/mail/?group_id=16191</ulink>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Bug tracker</term>
		<listitem><para>
			There is a bug tracker for OProfile at SourceForge,
			<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/p/oprofile/bugs/">http://sourceforge.net/p/oprofile/bugs/</ulink>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>IRC channel</term>
		<listitem><para>
			Several OProfile developers and users sometimes hang out on channel <command>#oprofile</command>
			on the <ulink url="http://oftc.net">OFTC</ulink> network. 
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="install">
<title>Installation</title>

<para>
First you need to build OProfile and install it. <command>./configure</command>, <command>make</command>, <command>make install</command>
is often all you need, but note these arguments to <command>./configure</command> :
</para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--with-java</option></term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			Use this option if you need to profile Java applications.  Also, see
			<xref linkend="requirements"/>, "Required user account".  This option
			is used to specify the location of the Java Development Kit (JDK)
			source tree you wish to use. This is necessary to get the interface description
			of the JVMPI (or JVMTI) interface to compile the JIT support code successfully.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
				The Java Runtime Environment (JRE) does not include the development
				files that are required to compile the JIT support code, so the full
				JDK must be installed in order to use this option.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
			By default, the Oprofile JIT support libraries will be installed in
			<filename>&lt;oprof_install_dir&gt;/lib/oprofile</filename>.  To build
			and install OProfile and the JIT support libraries as 64-bit, you can
			do something like the following:
			<screen>
			# CFLAGS="-m64" CXXFLAGS="-m64" ./configure \
			--with-java={my_jdk_installdir} \
			--libdir=/usr/local/lib64
			</screen>
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
				If you encounter errors building 64-bit, you should
				install libtool 1.5.26 or later since that release of
				libtool fixes known problems for certain platforms.
				If you install libtool into a non-standard location,
				you'll need to edit the invocation of 'aclocal' in
				OProfile's autogen.sh as follows (assume an install
				location of /usr/local):
				</para>
				<para>
				<code>aclocal -I m4 -I /usr/local/share/aclocal</code>
				</para>
			</note> 
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry id="disable-werror">
		<term><option>--disable-werror</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
			Development versions of OProfile build by
			default with <option>-Werror</option>. This option turns
			<option>-Werror</option> off.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry id="disable-optimization">
		<term><option>--disable-optimization</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
			Disable the <option>-O2</option> compiler flag
			(useful if you discover an OProfile bug and want to give a useful
			back-trace etc.)
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry id="with-kernel">
		<term><option>--with-kernel</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
			This option is used to specify the location of the kernel headers <filename>include</filename> directory
			needed to build the perf_events-enabled <command>operf</command> program. By default, the OProfile
			build system expects to find this directory under <filename>/usr</filename>. Use this option if your
			kernel headers are in a non-standard location or if building in a cross-compile enviroment or in a
			situation where the host system does not support perf_events but you wish to build binaries for a
			target system that does support perf_events.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
It is recommended that if you have a
uniprocessor machine, you enable the local APIC / IO_APIC support for
your kernel (this is automatically enabled for SMP kernels). With many BIOS (kernel &gt;= 2.6.9 and UP kernel)
it's not sufficient to enable the local APIC -- you must also turn it on explicitly at boot
time by providing the "lapic" option to the kernel.
If you use the NMI watchdog, be aware that the watchdog is disabled when profiling starts
and not re-enabled until the profiling is stopped.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="uninstall">
<title>Uninstalling OProfile</title>
<para>
You must have the source tree available to uninstall OProfile; a <command>make uninstall</command> will
remove all installed files except your configuration file in the directory <filename>~/.oprofile</filename>.
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>

<chapter id="overview"> 
<title>Overview</title>
<sect1 id="getting-started-with-operf">
<title>Getting started with OProfile using <command>operf</command></title>
<para>
Profiling with <command>operf</command> allows you to precisely target your profiling (i.e., single process
or system-wide). With <command>operf</command>, there is no initial setup needed -- simply invoke <command>operf</command> with
the options you need; then run the OProfile post-processing tool(s). The <command>operf</command> syntax
is as follows:
</para>
<screen>operf [ options ] [ --system-wide | --pid=&lt;PID&gt; | [ command [ args ] ] ]</screen>
<para>
A typical usage might look like this:
</para>
<screen>operf ./my_test_program my_arg</screen>
<para>
When <filename>./my_test_program</filename> completes (or when you press Ctrl-C), profiling
stops and you're ready to use <command>opreport</command> or other OProfile post-processing tools.
By default, <command>operf</command> stores the sample data in <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data/samples/current</filename>,
and <command>opreport</command> and other post-processing tools will look in that location first for profile data,
unless you pass the <code>--session-dir</code> option.
</para>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="getting-started-with-ocount">
<title>Getting started with OProfile using <command>ocount</command></title>
<para>
<command>ocount</command> is an OProfile tool that can be used to count native hardware events occurring in either
a specific application, a set of processes or threads, a set of active system processors, or the
entire system. The data collected during a counting session is displayed to stdout by default, but may
also be saved to a file.  The <command>ocount</command> syntax is as follows:
<para>
<screen>ocount [ options ] [ --system-wide | --process-list &lt;pids&gt; | --thread-list &lt;tids&gt; | --cpu-list &lt;cpus&gt; [ command [ args ] ] ]
</screen>
</para>
A typical usage might look like this:
<para>
<screen>ocount --events=CPU_CLK_UNHALTED,INST_RETIRED /home/user1/my_test_program my_arg</screen>
</para>
When <filename>my_test_program</filename> completes (or when you press Ctrl-C), counting
stops and the results are displayed to the screen (as shown below).
<para>
<screen>
Events were actively counted for 2.8 seconds.
Event counts (actual) for /home/user1/my_test_program:
	Event                   Count                    % time counted
	CPU_CLK_UNHALTED        9,408,018,070            100.00
	INST_RETIRED            16,719,918,108           100.00
</screen>
</para>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="eventspec">
<title>Specifying performance counter events</title>
<para>
Whether profiling with <command>operf</command> or doing simple event counting with <command>ocount</command>,
you can collect information about one more native hardware events using the <code>--events</code>
option -- a comma-separated list of event specfications. The event specification is the means to provide details
of how each hardware performance counter should be set up.
For profiling, the event specification is a colon-separated string of the form
<option><emphasis>name</emphasis>:<emphasis>count</emphasis>:<emphasis>unitmask</emphasis>:<emphasis>kernel</emphasis>:<emphasis>user</emphasis></option>
as described in the table below. For <command>ocount</command>, specification is of the form
<option><emphasis>name</emphasis>:<emphasis>unitmask</emphasis>:<emphasis>kernel</emphasis>:<emphasis>user</emphasis></option>.
Note the presence of the <emphasis>count</emphasis> field for profiling.  The <emphasis>count</emphasis> field tells the profiler
how many events should occur between a profile snapshot (usually referred to as a "sample").  Since
<command>ocount</command> does not do sampling, the <emphasis>count</emphasis> field is not needed.
</para>
<para>
If no event specs are passed to <command>operf</command> or <command>ocount</command>,
the default event will be used.
</para>
<para>
<note>The perf_events kernel subsystem allocates hardware counters as necessary, but some processor
types have restrictions as to what hardware events may be counted simultaneously.
The kernel employs a multiplexing technique when such
hardware restrictions are encountered, such that events are monitored on a rotating basis.
</note>
</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols='2'>
<tbody>
<row><entry><option>name</option></entry><entry>The symbolic event name, e.g. <constant>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED</constant></entry></row>
<row><entry><option>count</option></entry><entry>The counter reset value, e.g. 100000; use only for profiling</entry></row>
<row><entry><option>unitmask</option></entry><entry>The unit mask, as given in the events list: e.g. 0x0f; or a symbolic name
if a <constant>name=&lt;um_name&gt;</constant> field is present</entry></row>
<row><entry><option>kernel</option></entry><entry>Enable profiling of kernel code</entry></row>
<row><entry><option>user</option></entry><entry>Enable profiling of userspace code</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
The last three values are optional; if you omit them (e.g. <option>operf --events=DATA_MEM_REFS:30000</option>),
they will be set to the default values (i.e., the default unit mask value for the given event, and profiling (or counting)
both kernel and userspace code will be enabled). Note that on some architectures, some events may
require a unit mask be specified.
</para>
<para>
You can specify unit mask values using either a numerical value (hex values
<emphasis>must</emphasis> begin with "0x") or a symbolic name (if the <constant>name=&lt;um_name&gt;</constant>
field is shown in the <command>ophelp</command> output). For some named unit masks, the hex value is not unique; thus, OProfile
tools enforce specifying such unit masks value by name.
</para>
<para>
The table below lists the default profiling event for various processor types. The same events
can be used for <command>ocount</command>, minus the <emphasis>count</emphasis> field.
</para>
<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols='3'>
<tbody>
<row><entry>Processor</entry><entry>cpu_type</entry><entry>Default event</entry></row>
<row><entry>Alpha EV67</entry><entry>alpha/ev67</entry><entry>CYCLES:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>ARM/XScale PMU1</entry><entry>arm/xscale1</entry><entry>CPU_CYCLES:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>ARM/XScale PMU2</entry><entry>arm/xscale2</entry><entry>CPU_CYCLES:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>ARM/MPCore</entry><entry>arm/mpcore</entry><entry>CPU_CYCLES:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Athlon</entry><entry>i386/athlon</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium Pro</entry><entry>i386/ppro</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium II</entry><entry>i386/pii</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium III</entry><entry>i386/piii</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium M (P6 core)</entry><entry>i386/p6_mobile</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium 4 (non-HT)</entry><entry>i386/p4</entry><entry>GLOBAL_POWER_EVENTS:100000:1:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Pentium 4 (HT)</entry><entry>i386/p4-ht</entry><entry>GLOBAL_POWER_EVENTS:100000:1:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Hammer</entry><entry>x86-64/hammer</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Family10h</entry><entry>x86-64/family10</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Family11h</entry><entry>x86-64/family11h</entry><entry>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>IBM pseries</entry><entry>ppc64/power{ 4|5|6|7|8|970 }</entry><entry>CYCLES:100000:0:1:1</entry></row>
<row><entry>IBM s390</entry><entry>s390/{ z10|z196|zEC12 }</entry><entry>HWSAMPLING:4127518:0:1:1</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="tools-overview">
<title>Tools summary</title>
<para>
This section gives a brief description of the available OProfile utilities and their purpose.
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>ophelp</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This utility lists the available events and short descriptions.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>operf</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This is the program for collecting profile data, discussed in <xref linkend="controlling-operf" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
	
<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>ocount</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This tool is used for simple event counting, as described in in <xref linkend="controlling-ocount" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>agent libraries</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
			Used by virtual machines (like the Java VM) to record information about JITed code being profiled. See <xref linkend="setup-jit" />.
		</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>opreport</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This is the main tool for retrieving useful profile data, described in
		<xref linkend="opreport" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>opannotate</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This utility can be used to produce annotated source, assembly or mixed source/assembly.
		Source level annotation is available only if the application was compiled with 
		debugging symbols. See <xref linkend="opannotate" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>opgprof</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This utility can output gprof-style data files for a binary, for use with
		<command>gprof -p</command>. See <xref linkend="opgprof" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>oparchive</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This utility can be used to collect executables, debuginfo,
		and sample files and copy the files into an archive.
		The archive is self-contained and can be moved to another
		machine for further analysis.
		See <xref linkend="oparchive" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
	<term><filename>opimport</filename></term>
	<listitem><para>
		This utility converts sample database files from a foreign binary format (abi) to
		the native format. This is useful only when moving sample files between hosts
		for analysis on platforms other than the one used for collection.
		See <xref linkend="opimport" />.
	</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>
</sect1>
	
</chapter>

<chapter id="controlling-profiler">
<title>Controlling the profiler</title>

<sect1 id="controlling-operf">
<title>Using <command>operf</command></title>
<para>
This section describes in detail how <command>operf</command> is used to
control profiling. Unless otherwise directed, <command>operf</command> will profile using
the default event for your system. For most systems, the default event is some
cycles-based event, assuming your processor type supports hardware performance
counters. If your hardware <emphasis>does</emphasis> support performance counters, you can specify
something other than the default hardware event on which to profile. The performance
monitor counters can be programmed to count various hardware events,
such as cache misses or MMX operations. The event
chosen for each counter is reflected in the profile data collected
by OProfile: functions and binaries at the top of the profiles reflect
that most of the chosen events happened within that code.
</para>
<para>
Additionally, each counter is programmed with a "count" value, which corresponds to how
detailed the profile is. The lower the value, the more frequently profile
samples are taken. You can choose to sample only kernel code, user-space code,
or both (both is the default). Finally, some events have a "unit mask"
-- this is a value that further restricts the type of event being counted.
You can see the event types and unit masks for your CPU using <command>ophelp</command>.
More information on event specification can be found at <xref linkend="eventspec"/>.
</para>
<para>
The <command>operf</command> command syntax is:
</para>
<screen>operf [ options ] [ --system-wide | --pid=&lt;PID&gt; | [ command [ args ] ] ]</screen>
<para>
When profiling an application using either the <code>command</code> or <code>--pid</code> option of
<command>operf</command>, forks and execs of the profiled process will also be profiled. The samples
from an exec'ed process will be attributed to the executable binary run by that process. See
<xref linkend="interpreting_operf_results"/>
</para>
<para>
Following is a description of the <command>operf</command> options.
</para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>command [args]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The command or application to be profiled. The <emphasis>[args]</emphasis> are the input arguments
        that the command or application requires. Either <code>command</code>, <code>--pid</code> or
        <code>--system-wide</code> is required, but cannot be used simultaneously.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--pid / -p [PID]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option enables <command>operf</command> to profile a running application. <code>PID</code>
		should be the process ID of the process you wish to profile. When
		finished profiling (e.g., when the profiled process ends), press
		Ctrl-c to stop <command>operf</command>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--system-wide / -s</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option is for performing a system-wide profile. You must
		have root authority to run <command>operf</command> in this mode.
		When finished profiling, Ctrl-C to stop <command>operf</command>. If you run
		<code>operf --system-wide</code> as a background job (i.e., with the &amp;), you
		<emphasis>must</emphasis> stop it in a controlled manner in order to process
		the profile data it has collected.  Use <code>kill -SIGINT &lt;operf-PID&gt;</code>
		for this purpose. It is recommended that when running <command>operf</command>
		with this option, your current working directory should be <filename>/root</filename> or a subdirectory
		of <filename>/root</filename> to avoid storing sample data files in locations accessible by regular users.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--vmlinux / k [vmlinux_path]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		A vmlinux file that matches the running kernel that has symbol and/or debuginfo.
		Kernel samples will be attributed to this binary, allowing post-processing tools
		(like <command>opreport</command>) to attribute samples to the appropriate kernel symbols.
		If this option is not specified, the file /proc/kallsyms is used to obtain
		kernel symbol addresses correponding to sample addresses.  However, the setting of
		/proc/sys/kernel/kptr_restrict may restrict a non-root user's access to
		/proc/kallsyms, in which case,
		all kernel samples are attributed to a pseudo binary named "no-vmlinux".
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--callgraph / -g</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option enables the callgraph to be saved during profiling. NOTE: The
		full callchain is recorded, so there is no depth limit.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--append / -a</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		By default, <command>operf</command> moves old profile data from
		<filename>&lt;session_dir&gt;/samples/current</filename> to
		<filename>&lt;session_dir&gt;/samples/previous</filename>.
		If a 'previous' profile already existed, it will be replaced. If the
		<code>--append</code> option is passed, old profile data in 'current' is left in place and
		new profile data will be added to it, and the 'previous' profile (if one existed)
		will remain untouched. To access the 'previous' profile, simply add a session
		specification to the normal invocation of oprofile post-processing tools; for example:
		</para>
		<para>
		<screen>opreport session:previous</screen>
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--events / -e  [event1[,event2[,...]]]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option is for passing a comma-separated list of event specifications
		for profiling. Each event spec is of the form:
		</para>
		<screen>name:count[:unitmask[:kernel[:user]]]</screen>
		<para>
		When no event specification is given, the default event for the running
		processor type will be used for profiling. Use <command>ophelp</command>
		to list the available events for your processor type.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--separate-thread / -t</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option categorizes samples by thread group ID (tgid) and thread ID (tid).
		The <code>--separate-thread</code> option is useful for seeing per-thread samples in
		multi-threaded applications.  When used in conjuction with the <code>--system-wide</code>
		option, <code>--separate-thread</code> is also useful for seeing per-process
		(i.e., per-thread group) samples for the case where multiple processes are
		executing the same program during a profiling run.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--separate-cpu / -c</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option categorizes samples by cpu.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--session-dir / -d [path]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option specifies the session directory to hold the sample data. If not specified,
		the data is saved in the <filename>oprofile_data</filename> directory on the current path.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	   <term><option>---lazy-conversion / -l</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Use this option to reduce the overhead of <command>operf</command> during profiling.
		Normally, profile data received from the kernel is converted to OProfile format
		during profiling time. This is typically not an issue when profiling a single
		application. But when using the <code>--system-wide</code> option, this on-the-fly
		conversion process can cause noticeable overhead, particularly on busy
		multi-processor systems. The <code>--lazy-conversion</code> option directs
		<command>operf</command> to wait until profiling is completed to do the conversion
		of profile data.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--verbose / -V [level]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		A comma-separated list of debugging control values used to increase the verbosity of the
		output. Valid values are: debug, record, convert, misc, sfile, arcs, and the special value, 'all'.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--version -v </option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Show <command>operf</command> version.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--help / -h</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Show a help message.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="setup-jit">
	<title>Setting up the JIT profiling feature</title>
	<para>
		To gather information about JITed code from a virtual machine,
		it needs to be instrumented with an agent library. We use the
		agent libraries for Java in the following example. To use the
		Java profiling feature, you must build OProfile with the "--with-java" option
                (<xref linkend="install" />).

	</para>

	<sect2 id="setup-jit-jvm">
		<title>JVM instrumentation</title>
		<para>
			Add this to the startup parameters of the JVM (for JVMTI):

			<screen><option>-agentpath:&lt;libdir&gt;/libjvmti_oprofile.so[=&lt;options&gt;]</option> </screen>
			or
			<screen><option>-agentlib:jvmti_oprofile[=&lt;options&gt;]</option> </screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			The JVMPI agent implementation is enabled with the command line option
			<screen><option>-Xrunjvmpi_oprofile[:&lt;options&gt;]</option> </screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			Currently, there is just one option available -- <option>debug</option>. For JVMPI,
			the convention for specifying an option is <option>option_name=[yes|no]</option>.
			For JVMTI, the option specification is simply the option name, implying
			"yes"; no option specified implies "no".
		</para>
                <para>
                        The agent library (installed in <filename>&lt;oprof_install_dir&gt;/lib/oprofile</filename>)
                        needs to be in the library search path (e.g. add the library directory
                        to <constant>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</constant>). If the command line of
                        the JVM is not accessible, it may be buried within shell scripts or a
                        launcher program. It may also be possible to set an environment variable to add
                        the instrumentation.
                        For Sun JVMs this is <constant>JAVA_TOOL_OPTIONS</constant>. Please check
                        your JVM documentation for
                        further information on the agent startup options.
                </para>

	</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="detailed-parameters">
<title>Configuration details</title>

<sect2 id="hardware-counters">
<title>Hardware performance counters</title>
<para>Most processor models include performance monitor units that can be configured to monitor (count)
various types of hardware events.  This section is where you can find architecture-specific information
to help you use these events for profiling. You do not really need to read this section unless you are interested in using
events other than the default event chosen by OProfile.
</para>
<note>
<para>
Your CPU type may not include the requisite support for hardware performance counters, in which case
you must use OProfile in timer mode (see <xref linkend="timer" />), which is only available in
OProfile releases prior to 1.0.
</para>
</note>
<para>
The Intel hardware performance counters are detailed in the Intel IA-32 Architecture Manual, Volume 3, available
from <ulink url="http://developer.intel.com/">http://developer.intel.com/</ulink>. 
The AMD Athlon/Opteron/Phenom/Turion implementation is detailed in <ulink
url="http://www.amd.com/us-en/assets/content_type/white_papers_and_tech_docs/22007.pdf">
http://www.amd.com/us-en/assets/content_type/white_papers_and_tech_docs/22007.pdf</ulink>.
For IBM PowerPC processors, documentation is available at <ulink url="https://www.power.org/">
https://www.power.org/</ulink>. For example, <ulink url="https://www.power.org/events/Power7">
https://www.power.org/events/Power7</ulink> contains specific information on the performance
monitor unit for the IBM POWER7.
</para>
<para>
A physical performance monitor counter (PMC) is configured by a profiling tool to count a particular
type of event. When the counter overflows, an interrupt is delivered to the processor.
This is the basic mechanism on which OProfile is based. The delivery mode is <acronym>NMI</acronym>,
so blocking interrupts in the kernel does not prevent profiling. When the interrupt handler is called,
the current <acronym>PC</acronym> (program counter) value and the current task are recorded into the profiling structure.
This allows the overflow event to be attributed to a specific assembly instruction in a specific binary image.
OProfile receives this data (commonly referred to as a "sample") from the kernel and writes it to the sample files.
</para>
<para>
If we use an event such as <constant>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED</constant> or <constant>INST_RETIRED</constant>
(<constant>GLOBAL_POWER_EVENTS</constant> or <constant>INSTR_RETIRED</constant>, respectively, on the Pentium 4), we can
use the overflow counts (samples) as an estimate of actual time spent in each part of code. Alternatively we can profile interesting
data such as the cache behaviour of routines with the other available counters.
</para>
<para>
However there are several caveats. First, there are those issues listed in the Intel manual. There is a delay
between the counter overflow and the interrupt delivery that can skew results on a small scale - this means
you cannot rely on the profiles at the instruction level as being perfectly accurate.
For example, if you are profiling an application with an event that counts L1 cache misses, a sample attributed
to a particular instruction in the application doesn't necessarily mean that exact instruction is responsible
for that event; instead, it means the sample was taken in the dynamic vicinity of that instruction,
usually with a margin of error of a few instructions. Further details on this problem can be found in
<xref linkend="interpreting" /> and also in the Digital paper "ProfileMe: A Hardware Performance Counter".
</para>
<para>
Each counter has several configuration parameters besides the type of event to count.
First, there is the unit mask, which is used to further qualify exactly what to count.
Second, there is the <constant>count</constant> field, discussed below. Third, there are parameters
to specify whether to increment counts
whilst in kernel or user space. You can configure these separately for each counter.
</para>
<para>
When the profiler is initially setup, a performance monitor counter is chosen for counting the
event, and it is initialized using the <constant>count</constant> value.
Once profiling begins, the counter increments with each event detected, and the counter
<emphasis>overflows</emphasis> when the <constant>count</constant> value is reached.
As described above, the counter overflow generates an interrupt, and the sample is recorded.
After each overflow event, the counter is re-initialized using the <constant>count</constant> value,
and counting begins anew for the next sample. Higher values for <constant>count</constant>
result in samples being taken less frequently, and therefore less-detailed (and, potentially,
less accurate) profiling. Lower values mean more detail, but higher overhead.
Picking a good value for this parameter is, unfortunately, somewhat of a black art. It is
of course dependent on the event you have chosen.
Specifying too large a value will mean not enough interrupts are generated
to give a realistic profile (though this problem can be ameliorated by profiling for
longer time periods. Specifying too small a value can lead to higher performance overhead.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="timer">
<title>OProfile timer interrupt mode</title>
<para>
Some CPU types do not provide the needed hardware support for hardware performance counters.
Additionally, some older architectures are not supported by the perf_events kernel subsystem.
On such machines, the <command>operf</command> and <command>ocount</command> commands will exit with a message indicating the
processor type is not supported. However, you can install OProfile 0.9.9 and use the legacy
opcontrol-based profiler, which will fall back to using timer interrupts for profiling.
Note that in timer mode, OProfile is not able to profile code that has interrupts disabled.
<note>Timer mode is only available using the legacy <command>opcontrol</command> command,
available in releases prior to 1.0.</note>
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="special-notes">
<title>Architecture-specific configuration notes</title>
<sect3 id="p4">
<title>Pentium 4 support</title>
<para>
The Pentium 4 / Xeon performance counters are organized around 3 types of model specific registers (MSRs): 45 event
selection control registers (ESCRs), 18 counter configuration control registers (CCCRs) and 18 counters. ESCRs describe a
particular set of events which are to be recorded, and CCCRs bind ESCRs to counters and configure their
operation. Unfortunately the relationship between these registers is quite complex; they cannot all be used with one
another at any time. There is, however, a subset of 8 counters, 8 ESCRs, and 8 CCCRs which can be used independently of
one another, so OProfile only accesses those registers, treating them as a bank of 8 "normal" counters, similar
to those in the P6 or Athlon/Opteron/Phenom/Turion families of CPU.
</para>
<para>
There is currently no support for Precision Event-Based Sampling (PEBS), nor any advanced uses of the Debug Store
(DS). Current support is limited to the conservative extension of OProfile's existing interrupt-based model described
above.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="ppc64">
<title>PowerPC64 support</title>
<para>
The performance monitoring unit (PMU) for the IBM PowerPC 64-bit processors 
consists of between 4 and 8 counters (depending on the model).  Advanced features
such as instruction matching and thresholding are not supported by OProfile.
</para>

</sect3>
</sect2>



</sect1>

</chapter>

<chapter id="results">
<title>Obtaining profiling results</title>
<para>
After collecting profile data, the raw data must undergo special processing in order for you to
perform your analysis. The analysis tools that perform this special processing are
<command>opreport</command>, <command>opannotate</command>, and <command>opgprof</command>.
Additionally, the <command>oparchive</command> is used to gather together profile
data, sampled binary files, etc. for the purpose of off-line analysis.  While
not really an analysis tool, <command>oparchive</command> is put in that category
for convenience since it takes many of the same options as the other analysis tools.
</para>

<sect1 id="profile-spec">
<title>Profile specifications</title>

<para>
All of the analysis tools take a <emphasis>profile specification</emphasis>
as an input argument.
This is a set of definitions that describes the specific profile data that should be
examined. The simplest profile specification is empty: this will match all
the available profile files for the current session.
</para>
<para>
Specification parameters are of the form <option>name:value[,value]</option>.
For example, if I wanted to get a combined symbol summary for
<filename>/bin/myprog</filename> and <filename>/bin/myprog2</filename>,
I could do <command>opreport -l image:/bin/myprog,/bin/myprog2</command>.
As a special case, you don't actually need to specify the <option>image:</option>
part of the specification. Anything left on the command line after all other
<command>opreport</command> options have been processed is assumed to be an
<option>image:</option> name. Similarly, if no <option>session:</option>
is specified, then <option>session:current</option> is assumed ("current"
is a special name of the current (i.e., most recent) profiling session).
</para>
<para>
In addition to the comma-separated list shown above, some of the 
specification parameters can take <command>glob</command>-style
values. For example, if I want to see image summaries for all
binaries profiled in <filename>/usr/bin/</filename>, I could do
<command>opreport image:/usr/bin/\*</command>. Note the necessity
to escape the special character from the shell.
</para>
<para>
For <command>opreport</command>, profile specifications can be used to
define two profiles, giving differential output. This is done by
enclosing each of the two specifications within curly braces, as shown
in the examples below. Any specifications outside of curly braces are
shared across both.
</para>

<sect2 id="profile-spec-examples">
<title>Examples</title>

<para>
Image summaries for all profiles with <constant>DATA_MEM_REFS</constant>
samples in the saved session called "stresstest" :
</para>
<screen>
# opreport session:stresstest event:DATA_MEM_REFS
</screen>

<para>
Symbol summary for the application called "test_sym53c8xx,9xx". Note the
escaping is necessary as <option>image:</option> takes a comma-separated list.
</para>
<screen>
# opreport -l ./test/test_sym53c8xx\,9xx
</screen>

<para>
Image summaries for all binaries in the <filename>test</filename> directory,
excepting <filename>boring-test</filename> :
</para>
<screen>
# opreport image:./test/\* image-exclude:./test/boring-test
</screen>

<para>
Differential profile of a binary stored in two archives :
</para>
<screen>
# opreport -l /bin/bash { archive:./orig } { archive:./new }
</screen>

<para>
Differential profile of an archived binary with the current session :
</para>
<screen>
# opreport -l /bin/bash { archive:./orig } { }
</screen>

</sect2> <!-- profile spec examples -->

<sect2 id="profile-spec-details">
<title>Profile specification parameters</title>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>archive:</option><emphasis>archivepath</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		A path to an archive made with <command>oparchive</command>.
		Absence of this tag, unlike others, means "the current system",
		equivalent to specifying "archive:".
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>session:</option><emphasis>sessionlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		A comma-separated list of session names to resolve in. Absence of this
		tag, unlike others, means "the current session", equivalent to
		specifying "session:current".
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>session-exclude:</option><emphasis>sessionlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
                A comma-separated list of sessions to exclude.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>image:</option><emphasis>imagelist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
                A comma-separated list of image names to resolve. Each entry may be relative
                path, <command>glob</command>-style name, or full path, e.g.</para>
		<screen>opreport 'image:/usr/bin/oprofiled,*op*,./opreport'</screen>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>image-exclude:</option><emphasis>imagelist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Same as <option>image:</option>, but the matching images are excluded.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>lib-image:</option><emphasis>imagelist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Same as <option>image:</option>, but only for images that are for
		a particular primary binary image (namely, an application).
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>lib-image-exclude:</option><emphasis>imagelist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Same as <option>lib-image:</option>, but the matching images
		are excluded.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>event:</option><emphasis>eventlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The symbolic event name to match on, e.g. <option>event:DATA_MEM_REFS</option>.
		You can pass a list of events for side-by-side comparison with <command>opreport</command>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>count:</option><emphasis>eventcountlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The event count to match on, e.g. <option>event:DATA_MEM_REFS count:30000</option>.
		Note that this value refers to the count value in the event spec you passed
		to <command>operf</command> when setting up to do a
		profile run.  It has nothing to do with the sample counts in the profile data
		itself.
		You can pass a list of events for side-by-side comparison with <command>opreport</command>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>unit-mask:</option><emphasis>masklist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The unit mask value of the event to match on, e.g. <option>unit-mask:1</option>.
		You can pass a list of events for side-by-side comparison with <command>opreport</command>.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>cpu:</option><emphasis>cpulist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Only consider profiles for the given numbered CPU (starting from zero).
		This is only useful when using CPU profile separation.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>tgid:</option><emphasis>pidlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Only consider profiles for the given task groups. Unless some program
		is using threads, the task group ID of a process is the same
		as its process ID. This option corresponds to the POSIX
		notion of a thread group.
		This is only useful when using per-process profile separation.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>tid:</option><emphasis>tidlist</emphasis></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Only consider profiles for the given threads. When using
		recent thread libraries, all threads in a process share the
		same task group ID, but have different thread IDs. You can
		use this option in combination with <option>tgid:</option> to
		restrict the results to particular threads within a process.
		This is only useful when using per-process profile separation.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="locating-and-managing-binary-images">
<title>Locating and managing binary images</title>
<para>
Each session's sample files can be found in the $SESSION_DIR/samples/ directory (default
for <command>operf</command> is <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data/samples/</filename>).
These are used, along with the binary image files, to produce human-readable data.
In some circumstances (e.g., kernel modules), OProfile
will not be able to find the binary images. All the tools have an <option>--image-path</option>
option to which you can pass a comma-separated list of alternate paths to search. For example,
I can let OProfile find my 2.6 modules by using <command>--image-path /lib/modules/2.6.0/kernel/</command>.
It is your responsibility to ensure that the correct images are found when using this
option.
</para>
<para>
Note that if a binary image changes after the sample file was created, you won't be able to get useful
symbol-based data out. This situation is detected for you. If you replace a binary, you should
make sure to save the old binary if you need to do comparative profiles.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="no-results">
<title>What to do when you don't get any results</title>
<para>
When attempting to get output, you may see the error :
</para>
<screen>
error: no sample files found: profile specification too strict ?
</screen>
<para>
What this is saying is that the profile specification you passed in,
when matched against the available sample files, resulted in no matches.
There are a number of reasons this might happen:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term>spelling</term><listitem><para>
You specified a binary name, but spelt it wrongly. Check your spelling !
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>profiler wasn't running</term><listitem><para>
Make very sure that OProfile was actually up and running when you ran
the application you wish to profile.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>application didn't run long enough</term><listitem><para>
Remember OProfile is a statistical profiler - you're not guaranteed to
get samples for short-running programs. You can help this by using a
lower count for the performance counter, so there are a lot more samples
taken per second.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>application spent most of its time in libraries</term><listitem><para>
Similarly, if the application spends little time in the main binary image
itself, with most of it spent in shared libraries it uses, you might
not see any samples for the binary image (i.e., executable) itself.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>specification was really too strict</term><listitem><para>
For example, you specified something like <option>tgid:3433</option>,
but no task with that group ID ever ran the code.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>application didn't generate any events</term><listitem><para>
If you're profiling a particular event, for example counting MMX
operations, the code might simply have not generated any events in the
first place. Verify the code you're profiling does what you expect it
to.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>you didn't specify kernel module name correctly</term><listitem><para>
If you're trying to get reports for a kernel
module, make sure to use the <option>-p</option> option, and specify the
module name <emphasis>with</emphasis> the <filename>.ko</filename>
extension. Check if the module is one loaded from initrd.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- profile-spec -->

<sect1 id="opreport">
<title>Image summaries and symbol summaries (<command>opreport</command>)</title>
<para>
The <command>opreport</command> utility is the primary utility you will use for 
getting formatted data out of OProfile. It produces two types of data: image summaries
and symbol summaries. An image summary lists the number of samples for individual
binary images such as libraries or applications. Symbol summaries provide per-symbol
profile data. In the following truncated example, we see an image summary for the whole
system:
</para>
<screen>
$ opreport --long-filenames
CPU: Intel Sandy Bridge microarchitecture, speed 2401 MHz (estimated)
Counted CPU_CLK_UNHALTED events (Clock cycles when not halted) with a unit mask of 0x00 (No unit mask) count 100000
CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
  samples|      %|
------------------
    22577 28.9011 /usr/bin/Xorg
        CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
          samples|      %|
        ------------------
            16846 74.6158 /proc/kallsyms
             2126  9.4167 /usr/bin/Xorg
              763  3.3795 /usr/lib64/libpixman-1.so.0.26.2
              ...
    17402 22.2766 /usr/lib/jvm/java-1.7.0-openjdk-1.7.0.55.x86_64/jre/bin/java
        CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
          samples|      %|
        ------------------
             5666 32.5595 anon (tgid:29664 range:0x7f3475000000-0x7f347616ffff)
             2312 13.2858 /usr/lib/jvm/java-1.7.0-openjdk-1.7.0.55.x86_64/jre/lib/amd64/server/libjvm.so
             ...
    11554 14.7904 /home/user1/oprof-install/bin/operf
        CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
          samples|      %|
        ------------------
             7467 64.6270 /proc/kallsyms
             1691 14.6356 /usr/bin/operf
             1324 11.4592 /lib64/libc-2.12.so
              455  3.9380 /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6.0.13
              315  2.7263 /ext4
              ...
    ...
</screen>
<para>
If we had specified <option>--symbols</option> in the previous command, we would have
gotten a symbol summary of all the images across the entire system. We can restrict this to only
part of the system profile; for example,
below is a symbol summary for the <command>operf</command> program used to collect the profile.
</para>
<screen>
$ opreport -l -p /lib/modules/`uname -r` `which operf` 2>/dev/null | more
CPU: Intel Sandy Bridge microarchitecture, speed 2401 MHz (estimated)
Counted CPU_CLK_UNHALTED events (Clock cycles when not halted) with a unit mask of 0x00 (No unit mask) count 100000
samples  %        image name               symbol name
860       7.4607  kallsyms                 avtab_search_node
474       4.1121  operf                    OP_perf_utils::op_write_event(event_union*, unsigned long long)
461       3.9993  kallsyms                 avc_has_perm_noaudit
455       3.9473  libstdc++.so.6.0.13      /usr/lib64/libstdc++.so.6.0.13
412       3.5742  libc-2.12.so             _IO_vfscanf
369       3.2012  kallsyms                 __d_lookup
350       3.0363  kallsyms                 sidtab_context_to_sid
274       2.3770  operf                    OP_perf_utils::op_record_process_exec_mmaps(int, int, int, operf_record*)
232       2.0127  operf                    operf_process_info::find_mapping_for_sample(unsigned long long, bool)
222       1.9259  kallsyms                 __link_path_walk
191       1.6570  kallsyms                 pipe_read
34        0.2950  ext4.ko                  ext4_mark_iloc_dirty
...
</screen>

<para>
These are the two basic ways you are most likely to use regularly, but <command>opreport</command>
can do a lot more than that, as described below.
</para>

<sect2 id="opreport-merging">
<title>Merging separate profiles</title>

If you have used one of the <option>--separate[*]</option> options
whilst profiling, there can be several separate profiles for
a single binary image within a session. Normally the output
will keep these images separated. So, for example, if you profiled
with separation on a per-cpu basis (<code>operf --separate-cpu</code>),
you would see separate columns in
the output of <command>opreport</command> for each CPU where samples
were recorded. But it can be useful to merge these results back together
to make the report more readable. The <option>--merge</option> option allows
you to do that.
</sect2>

<sect2 id="opreport-comparison">
<title>Side-by-side multiple results</title>
If you have used multiple events when profiling, by default you get
side-by-side results of each event's sample values from <command>opreport</command>.
You can restrict which events to list by appropriate use of the
<option>event:</option> profile specifications, etc.
</sect2>

<sect2 id="opreport-callgraph">
<title>Callgraph output</title>
<para>
This section provides details on how to use the OProfile callgraph feature.
</para>
<sect3 id="op-cg1">
<title>Callgraph details</title>
<para>
When using the <option>--callgraph</option> option, you can see what
functions are calling other functions in the output. Consider the
following program:
</para>
<screen>
#include &lt;string.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;

#define SIZE 500000

static int compare(const void *s1, const void *s2)
{
        return strcmp(s1, s2);
}

static void repeat(void)
{
        int i;
        char *strings[SIZE];
        char str[] = "abcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz";

        for (i = 0; i &lt; SIZE; ++i) {
                strings[i] = strdup(str);
                strfry(strings[i]);
        }

        qsort(strings, SIZE, sizeof(char *), compare);
}

int main()
{
        while (1)
                repeat();
}
</screen>
<para>
When running with the call-graph option, OProfile will
record the function stack every time it takes a sample.
<command>opreport --callgraph</command> outputs an entry for each
function, where each entry looks similar to:
</para>
<screen>
samples  %        image name               symbol name
  197       0.1548  cg                       main
  127036   99.8452  cg                       repeat
84590    42.5084  libc-2.3.2.so            strfry
  84590    66.4838  libc-2.3.2.so            strfry [self]
  39169    30.7850  libc-2.3.2.so            random_r
  3475      2.7312  libc-2.3.2.so            __i686.get_pc_thunk.bx
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
</screen>
<para>
Here the non-indented line is the function we're focussing upon
(<function>strfry()</function>). This
line is the same as you'd get from a normal <command>opreport</command>
output.
</para>
<para>
Above the non-indented line we find the functions that called this
function (for example, <function>repeat()</function> calls
<function>strfry()</function>). The samples and percentage values here
refer to the number of times we took a sample where this call was found
in the stack; the percentage is relative to all other callers of the
function we're focussing on. Note that these values are
<emphasis>not</emphasis> call counts; they only reflect the call stack
every time a sample is taken; that is, if a call is found in the stack
at the time of a sample, it is recorded in this count.
</para>
<para>
Below the line are functions that are called by
<function>strfry()</function> (called <emphasis>callees</emphasis>).
It's clear here that <function>strfry()</function> calls
<function>random_r()</function>. We also see a special entry with a
"[self]" marker. This records the normal samples for the function, but
the percentage becomes relative to all callees. This allows you to
compare time spent in the function itself compared to functions it
calls. Note that if a function calls itself, then it will appear in the
list of callees of itself, but without the "[self]" marker; so recursive
calls are still clearly separable.
</para>
<para>
You may have noticed that the output lists <function>main()</function>
as calling <function>strfry()</function>, but it's clear from the source
that this doesn't actually happen. See <xref
linkend="interpreting-callgraph" /> for an explanation.
</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="cg-with-jitsupport">
<title>Callgraph is not supported with JIT samples</title>
<para>
Callgraph output where anonymously mapped code is in the callstack can sometimes be misleading.
For all such code, the samples for the anonymously mapped code are stored in a samples subdirectory
named <filename>{anon:anon}/&lt;tgid&gt;.&lt;begin_addr&gt;.&lt;end_addr&gt;</filename>.
As stated earlier, if this anonymously mapped code is JITed code from a supported VM like Java,
OProfile creates an ELF file to provide a (somewhat) permanent backing file for the code.
However, when viewing callgraph output, any anonymously mapped code in the callstack
will be attributed to <filename>anon (&lt;tgid&gt;: range:&lt;begin_addr&gt;-&lt;end_addr&gt;</filename>,
even if a <filename>.jo</filename> ELF file had been created for it.  See the example below.
</para>
<screen>
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
  1         2.2727  libj9ute23.so            java.bin                 traceV
  2         4.5455  libj9ute23.so            java.bin                 utsTraceV
  4         9.0909  libj9trc23.so            java.bin                 fillInUTInterfaces
  37       84.0909  libj9trc23.so            java.bin                 twGetSequenceCounter
8         0.0154  libj9prt23.so            java.bin                 j9time_hires_clock
  27       61.3636  anon (tgid:10014 range:0x100000-0x103000) java.bin                 (no symbols)
  9        20.4545  libc-2.4.so              java.bin                 gettimeofday
  8        18.1818  libj9prt23.so            java.bin                 j9time_hires_clock [self]
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
</screen>
<para>
The output shows that "anon (tgid:10014 range:0x100000-0x103000)" was a callee of
<code>j9time_hires_clock</code>, even though the ELF file <filename>10014.jo</filename> was
created for this profile run.  Unfortunately, there is currently no way to correlate
that anonymous callgraph entry with its corresponding <filename>.jo</filename> file.
</para>
</sect3>


</sect2> <!-- opreport-callgraph -->

<sect2 id="opreport-diff">
<title>Differential profiles with <command>opreport</command></title>

<para>
Often, we'd like to be able to compare two profiles. For example, when
analysing the performance of an application, we'd like to make code
changes and examine the effect of the change. This is supported in
<command>opreport</command> by giving a profile specification that
identifies two different profiles. The general form is of:
</para>
<screen>
$ opreport &lt;shared-spec&gt; { &lt;first-profile&gt; } { &lt;second-profile&gt; }
</screen>
<note><para>
We lost our Dragon book down the back of the sofa, so you have to be
careful to have spaces around those braces, or things will get
hopelessly confused. We can only apologise.
</para></note>
<para>
For each of the profiles, the shared section is prefixed, and then the
specification is analysed. The usual parameters work both within the
shared section, and in the sub-specification within the curly braces.
</para>
<para>
A typical way to use this feature is with archives created with
<command>oparchive</command>. Let's look at an example:
</para>
<screen>
$ operf ./a
$ oparchive -o orig ./a
  # edit and recompile a
$ operf ./a
  # now compare the current profile of a with the archived profile
$ opreport  --session-dir=`pwd`/oprofile_data/ -xl ./a { archive:./orig } { }
CPU: PIII, speed 863.233 MHz (estimated)
Counted CPU_CLK_UNHALTED events (clocks processor is not halted) with a
unit mask of 0x00 (No unit mask) count 100000
samples  %        diff %    symbol name
92435    48.5366  +0.4999   a
54226    ---      ---       c
49222    25.8459  +++       d
48787    25.6175  -2.2e-01  b
</screen>
<para>
Note that we specified an empty second profile in the curly braces, as
we wanted to use the current session; alternatively, we could
have specified another archive, or a tgid etc. We specified the binary
<command>a</command> in the shared section, so we matched that in both
the profiles we're diffing.
</para>
<para>
As in the normal output, the results are sorted by the number of
samples, and the percentage field represents the relative percentage of
the symbol's samples in the second profile.
</para>
<para>
Notice the new column in the output. This value represents the
percentage change of the relative percent between the first and the
second profile: roughly, "how much more important this symbol is".
Looking at the symbol <function>a()</function>, we can see that it took
roughly the same amount of the total profile in both the first and the
second profile. The function <function>c()</function> was not in the new
profile, so has been marked with <function>---</function>. Note that the
sample value is the number of samples in the first profile; since we're
displaying results for the second profile, we don't list a percentage
value for it, as it would be meaningless. <function>d()</function> is
new in the second profile, and consequently marked with
<function>+++</function>.
</para>
<para>
When comparing profiles between different binaries, it should be clear
that functions can change in terms of VMA and size. To avoid this
problem, <command>opreport</command> considers a symbol to be the same
if the symbol name, image name, and owning application name all match;
any other factors are ignored. Note that the check for application name
means that trying to compare library profiles between two different
applications will not work as you might expect: each symbol will be
considered different.
</para>

</sect2> <!-- opreport-diff -->

<sect2 id="opreport-anon">
<title>Anonymous executable mappings</title>
<para>
Many applications, typically ones involving dynamic compilation into
machine code (just-in-time, or "JIT", compilation), have executable mappings that
are not backed by an ELF file. <command>opreport</command> has basic support for showing the
samples taken in these regions; for example:
<screen>
$ opreport /usr/bin/mono -l
CPU: ppc64 POWER5, speed 1654.34 MHz (estimated)
Counted CYCLES events (Processor Cycles using continuous sampling) with a unit mask of 0x00 (No unit mask) count 100000
samples  %        image name    		                symbol name
47       58.7500  mono                     			(no symbols)
14       17.5000  anon (tgid:3189 range:0xf72aa000-0xf72fa000)  (no symbols)
9        11.2500  anon (tgid:3189 range:0xf6cca000-0xf6dd9000)  (no symbols)
.	 .	  .						.
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Note that, since such mappings are dependent upon individual invocations of
a binary, these mappings are always listed as a dependent image.
Equally, the results are not affected by the <option>--merge</option>
option.
</para>
<para>
As shown in the opreport output above, OProfile is unable to attribute the samples to any
symbol(s) because there is no ELF file for this code.
Enhanced support for JITed code is now available for some virtual machines; 
e.g., the Java Virtual Machine.  For details about OProfile output for
JITed code, see <xref linkend="getting-jit-reports" />.
</para>
<para>For more information about JIT support in OProfile, see <xref linkend="jitsupport"/>.
</para>
</sect2> <!-- opreport-anon -->

<sect2 id="opreport-xml">
<title>XML formatted output</title>
<para>
The --xml option can be used to generate XML instead of the usual
text format.  This allows opreport to eliminate some of the constraints
dictated by the two dimensional text format.  For example, it is possible
to separate the sample data across multiple events, cpus and threads.  The XML
schema implemented by opreport is found in doc/opreport.xsd. It contains
more detailed comments about the structure of the XML generated by opreport.
</para>
<para>
Since XML is consumed by a client program rather than a user, its structure
is fairly static.  In particular, the --sort option is incompatible with the
--xml option.  Percentages are not dislayed in the XML so the options related
to percentages will have no effect.  Full pathnames are always displayed in
the XML so --long-filenames is not necessary.  The --details option will cause
all of the individual sample data to be included in the XML as well as the
instruction byte stream for each symbol (for doing disassembly) and can result
in very large XML files.
</para>
</sect2> <!-- opreport-xml -->

<sect2 id="opreport-options">
<title>Options for <command>opreport</command></title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--accumulated / -a</option></term><listitem><para>
Accumulate sample and percentage counts in the symbol list.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--callgraph / -c</option></term><listitem><para>
Show callgraph information.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--debug-info / -g</option></term><listitem><para>
Show source file and line for each symbol.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--demangle / -D none|normal|smart</option></term><listitem><para>
none: no demangling. normal: use default demangler (default) smart: use
pattern-matching to make C++ symbol demangling more readable.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--details / -d</option></term><listitem><para>
Show per-instruction details for all selected symbols. Note that, for
binaries without symbol information, the VMA values shown are raw file
offsets for the image binary.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-dependent / -x</option></term><listitem><para>
Do not include application-specific images for libraries, kernel modules
and the kernel..
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-symbols / -e [symbols]</option></term><listitem><para>
Exclude all the symbols in the given comma-separated list.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--global-percent / -%</option></term><listitem><para>
Make all percentages relative to the whole profile.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--help / -? / --usage</option></term><listitem><para>
Show help message.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--image-path / -p [paths]</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of additional paths to search for binaries.
This is needed to find kernel modules.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--root / -R [path]</option></term><listitem><para>
A path to a filesystem to search for additional binaries.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--include-symbols / -i [symbols]</option></term><listitem><para>
Only include symbols in the given comma-separated list.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--long-filenames / -f</option></term><listitem><para>
Output full paths instead of basenames.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--merge / -m [lib,cpu,tid,tgid,unitmask,all]</option></term><listitem><para>
Merge any profiles separated in a --separate session.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--no-header</option></term><listitem><para>
Don't output a header detailing profiling parameters.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--output-file / -o [file]</option></term><listitem><para>
Output to the given file instead of stdout.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--reverse-sort / -r</option></term><listitem><para>
Reverse the sort from the default.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--session-dir=dir_path</option></term><listitem><para>
Use sample database from the specified directory <filename>dir_path</filename> instead
of the default location. If this option is not specified, then opreport will search for
samples in <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data</filename>
first. If that directory does not exist, the standard session-dir of
<filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename> is used
as the session directory.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--show-address / -w</option></term><listitem><para>
Show the VMA address of each symbol (off by default).
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--sort / -s [vma,sample,symbol,debug,image]</option></term><listitem><para>
Sort the list of symbols by, respectively, symbol address,
number of samples, symbol name, debug filename and line number,
binary image filename.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--symbols / -l</option></term><listitem><para>
List per-symbol information instead of a binary image summary.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--threshold / -t [percentage]</option></term><listitem><para>
Only output data for symbols that have more than the given percentage
of total samples. For profiles using multiple events, if the threshold is reached
for any event, then all sample data for the symbol is shown.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--verbose / -V [options]</option></term><listitem><para>
Give verbose debugging output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--version / -v</option></term><listitem><para>
Show version.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--xml / -X</option></term><listitem><para>
Generate XML output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

</sect1> <!-- opreport -->

<sect1 id="opannotate">
<title>Outputting annotated source (<command>opannotate</command>)</title>
<para>
The <command>opannotate</command> utility generates annotated source files or assembly listings, optionally
mixed with source.
If you want to see the source file, the profiled application needs to have debug information, and the source
must be available through this debug information. For GCC, you must use the <option>-g</option> option
when you are compiling.
If the binary doesn't contain sufficient debug information, you can still
use <command>opannotate <option>--assembly</option></command> to get annotated assembly
as long as the binary has (at least) symbol information.
</para>
<para>
Note that for the reason explained in <xref linkend="hardware-counters" /> the results can be
inaccurate. The debug information itself can add other problems; for example, the line number for a symbol can be
incorrect. Assembly instructions can be re-ordered and moved by the compiler, and this can lead to
crediting source lines with samples not really "owned" by this line. Also see
<xref linkend="interpreting" />.
</para>
<para>
You can output the annotation to one single file, containing all the source found using the
<option>--source</option>. You can use this in conjunction with <option>--assembly</option>
to get combined source/assembly output.
</para>
<para>
You can also output a directory of annotated source files that maintains the structure of
the original sources. Each line in the annotated source is prepended with the samples
for that line. Additionally, each symbol is annotated giving details for the symbol
as a whole. An example:
</para>
<screen>
$ opannotate --source --output-dir=annotated /usr/local/oprofile-pp/bin/oprofiled
$ ls annotated/home/moz/src/oprofile-pp/daemon/
opd_cookie.h  opd_image.c  opd_kernel.c  opd_sample_files.c  oprofiled.c
</screen>
<para>
Line numbers are maintained in the source files, but each file has
a footer appended describing the profiling details. The actual annotation
looks something like this :
</para>
<screen>
...
               :static uint64_t pop_buffer_value(struct transient * trans)
 11510  1.9661 :{ /* pop_buffer_value total:  89901 15.3566 */
               :        uint64_t val;
               :
 10227  1.7469 :        if (!trans->remaining) {
               :                fprintf(stderr, "BUG: popping empty buffer !\n");
               :                exit(EXIT_FAILURE);
               :        }
               :
               :        val = get_buffer_value(trans->buffer, 0);
  2281  0.3896 :        trans->remaining--;
  2296  0.3922 :        trans->buffer += kernel_pointer_size;
               :        return val;
 10454  1.7857 :}
...
</screen>

<para>
The first number on each line is the number of samples, whilst the second is
the relative percentage of total samples.
</para>

<sect2 id="opannotate-finding-source">
<title>Locating source files</title>
<para>
Of course, <command>opannotate</command> needs to be able to locate the source files
for the binary image(s) in order to produce output. Some binary images have debug
information where the given source file paths are relative, not absolute. You can
specify search paths to look for these files (similar to <command>gdb</command>'s
<option>dir</option> command) with the <option>--search-dirs</option> option.
</para>
<para>
Sometimes you may have a binary image which gives absolute paths for the source files,
but you have the actual sources elsewhere (commonly, you've installed an SRPM for
a binary on your system and you want annotation from an existing profile). You can
use the <option>--base-dirs</option> option to redirect OProfile to look somewhere
else for source files. For example, imagine we have a binary generated from a source
file that is given in the debug information as <filename>/tmp/build/libfoo/foo.c</filename>,
and you have the source tree matching that binary installed in <filename>/home/user/libfoo/</filename>.
You can redirect OProfile to find <filename>foo.c</filename> correctly like this :
</para>
<screen>
$ opannotate --source --base-dirs=/tmp/build/libfoo/ --search-dirs=/home/user/libfoo/ --output-dir=annotated/ /lib/libfoo.so
</screen>
<para>
You can specify multiple (comma-separated) paths to both options.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="opannotate-details">
<title>Usage of <command>opannotate</command></title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--assembly / -a</option></term><listitem><para>
Output annotated assembly. If this is combined with --source, then mixed
source / assembly annotations are output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--base-dirs / -b [paths]/</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of path prefixes. This can be used to point OProfile to a
different location for source files when the debug information specifies an
absolute path on your system for the source that does not exist. The prefix
is stripped from the debug source file paths, then searched in the search dirs
specified by <option>--search-dirs</option>.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--demangle / -D none|normal|smart</option></term><listitem><para>
none: no demangling. normal: use default demangler (default) smart: use
pattern-matching to make C++ symbol demangling more readable.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-dependent / -x</option></term><listitem><para>
Do not include application-specific images for libraries, kernel modules
and the kernel.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-file [files]</option></term><listitem><para>
Exclude all files in the given comma-separated list of glob patterns.
This option is supported solely with the <code>--source</code>
option. It can be used to filter out source files in the output using the
following types of specifications:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>filenames (basename -- i.e., no path)</listitem>
<listitem>filename glob specifications (all files whose base filename matches the given pattern)</listitem>
<listitem>directory segments (all source files located in the specified directory; e.g. "libio")</listitem>
<listitem>directory segment glob specifications (e.g., "libi*")</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-symbols / -e [symbols]</option></term><listitem><para>
Exclude all the symbols in the given comma-separated list.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--help / -? / --usage</option></term><listitem><para>
Show help message.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--image-path / -p [paths]</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of additional paths to search for binaries.
This is needed to find kernel modules.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--root / -R [path]</option></term><listitem><para>
A path to a filesystem to search for additional binaries.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--include-file [files]</option></term><listitem><para>
Only include files in the given comma-separated list of glob patterns.
The same rules apply for this option as for the <code>--exclude-file</code> option.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--include-symbols / -i [symbols]</option></term><listitem><para>
Only include symbols in the given comma-separated list.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--objdump-params [params]</option></term><listitem><para>
Pass the given parameters as extra values when calling objdump.
If more than one option is to be passed to objdump, the parameters must be enclosed in a
quoted string.
</para>
<para>
An example of where this option is useful is when your toolchain does not
automatically recognize instructions that are specific to your processor.
For example, on IBM POWER7/RHEL 6, objdump must be told that a binary file may have
POWER7-specific instructions. The <command>opannotate</command> option to show the POWER7-specific
instructions is:
<screen>
   --objdump-params=-Mpower7
</screen>
</para>
<para>
The <command>opannotate</command> option to show the POWER7-specific instructions,
the source code (--source) and the line numbers (-l) would be:
<screen>
   --objdump-params="-Mpower7 -l --source"
</screen>
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--output-dir / -o [dir]</option></term><listitem><para>
Output directory. This makes opannotate output one annotated file for each
source file. This option can't be used in conjunction with --assembly.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--search-dirs / -d [paths]</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of paths to search for source files. This is useful to find
source files when the debug information only contains relative paths.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--source / -s</option></term><listitem><para>
Output annotated source. This requires debugging information to be available
for the binaries.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--session-dir=dir_path</option></term><listitem><para>
Use sample database from the specified directory <filename>dir_path</filename> instead
of the default location. If this option is not specified, then opannotate will search for
samples in <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data</filename>
first. If that directory does not exist, the standard session-dir of
<filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename> is used
as the session directory.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--threshold / -t [percentage]</option></term><listitem><para>
For annotated assembly, only output data for symbols that have more than the given percentage
of total samples. For profiles using multiple events, if the threshold is reached
for any event, then all sample data for the symbol is shown.
</para>
<para>
For annotated source, only output data for source files that have more than the given percentage
of total samples. For profiles using multiple events, if the threshold is reached
for any event, then all sample data for the source file is shown.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--verbose / -V [options]</option></term><listitem><para>
Give verbose debugging output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--version / -v</option></term><listitem><para>
Show version.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>


</sect2> <!-- opannotate-details -->

</sect1> <!-- opannotate -->

<sect1 id="getting-jit-reports">
	<title>OProfile results with JIT samples</title>
	<para>
		After profiling a Java (or other supported VM) application, the
		OProfile JIT support creates ELF binaries from the
		intermediate files that were written by the agent library.
		The ELF binaries are named <filename>&lt;tgid&gt;.jo</filename>.
		With the symbol information stored in these ELF files, it is
		possible to map samples to the appropriate symbols.
	</para>
	<para>
		The usual analysis tools (<command>opreport</command> and/or 
		<command>opannotate</command>) can now be used
		to get symbols and assembly code for the instrumented VM processes.
	</para>
<para>
Below is an example of a profile report of a Java application that has been
instrumented with the provided agent library.
<screen>
$ opreport -l /usr/lib/jvm/jre-1.5.0-ibm/bin/java
CPU: Core Solo / Duo, speed 2167 MHz (estimated)
Counted CPU_CLK_UNHALTED events (Unhalted clock cycles) with a unit mask of 0x00 (Unhalted core cycles) count 100000
samples  %        image name               symbol name
186020   50.0523  no-vmlinux               no-vmlinux               (no symbols)
34333     9.2380  7635.jo                  java                     void test.f1()
19022     5.1182  libc-2.5.so              libc-2.5.so              _IO_file_xsputn@@GLIBC_2.1
18762     5.0483  libc-2.5.so              libc-2.5.so              vfprintf
16408     4.4149  7635.jo                  java                     void test$HelloThread.run()
16250     4.3724  7635.jo                  java                     void test$test_1.f2(int)
15303     4.1176  7635.jo                  java                     void test.f2(int, int)
13252     3.5657  7635.jo                  java                     void test.f2(int)
5165      1.3897  7635.jo                  java                     void test.f4()
955       0.2570  7635.jo                  java                     void test$HelloThread.run()~

</screen>
</para>
<note><para>
	  Depending on the JVM that is used, certain options of opreport and opannotate
	  do NOT work since they rely on debug information (e.g. source code line number)
	  that is not always available. The Sun JVM does provide the necessary debug
	  information via the JVMTI[PI] interface,
	  but other JVMs do not.
  </para></note>
	<para>
		As you can see in the opreport output, the JIT support agent for Java
		generates symbols to include the class and method signature.
		A symbol with the suffix &tilde;&lt;n&gt; (e.g.
		<code>void test$HelloThread.run()&tilde;1</code>) means that this is
		the &lt;n&gt;th occurrence of the identical name. This happens if a method is re-JITed.
		A symbol with the suffix %&lt;n&gt;, means that the address space of this symbol
		was reused during the sample session (see <xref linkend="overlapping-symbols" />).
		The value &lt;n&gt; is the percentage of time that this symbol/code was present in
		relation to the total lifetime of all overlapping other symbols. A symbol of the form
		<code>&lt;return_val&gt; &lt;class_name&gt;$&lt;method_sig&gt;</code> denotes an
		inner class.
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="opgprof">
<title><command>gprof</command>-compatible output (<command>opgprof</command>)</title>
<para>
If you're familiar with the output produced by <command>GNU gprof</command>,
you may find <command>opgprof</command> useful. It takes a single binary
as an argument, and produces a <filename>gmon.out</filename> file for use
with <command>gprof -p</command>. If call-graph profiling is enabled,
then this is also included.
</para>
<screen>
$ opgprof `which oprofiled` # generates gmon.out file
$ gprof -p `which oprofiled` | head
Flat profile:

Each sample counts as 1 samples.
  %   cumulative   self              self     total
 time   samples   samples    calls  T1/call  T1/call  name
 33.13 206237.00 206237.00                             odb_insert
 22.67 347386.00 141149.00                             pop_buffer_value
  9.56 406881.00 59495.00                             opd_put_sample
  7.34 452599.00 45718.00                             opd_find_image
  7.19 497327.00 44728.00                             opd_process_samples
</screen>

<sect2 id="opgprof-details">
<title>Usage of <command>opgprof</command></title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--help / -? / --usage</option></term><listitem><para>
Show help message.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--image-path / -p [paths]</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of additional paths to search for binaries.
This is needed to find kernel modules.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--root / -R [path]</option></term><listitem><para>
A path to a filesystem to search for additional binaries.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--output-filename / -o [file]</option></term><listitem><para>
Output to the given file instead of the default, gmon.out
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--threshold / -t [percentage]</option></term><listitem><para>
Only output data for symbols that have more than the given percentage
of total samples.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--verbose / -V [options]</option></term><listitem><para>
Give verbose debugging output.
<varlistentry><term><option>--session-dir=dir_path</option></term><listitem><para>
Use sample database from the specified directory <filename>dir_path</filename> instead
of the default location. If this option is not specified, then opgprof will search for
samples in <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data</filename>
first. If that directory does not exist, the standard session-dir of
<filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename> is used
as the session directory.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--version / -v</option></term><listitem><para>
Show version.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2> <!-- opgprof-details -->

</sect1> <!-- opgprof -->

<sect1 id="oparchive">
<title>Analyzing profile data on another system (<command>oparchive</command>)</title>
<para>
	The <command>oparchive</command> utility generates a directory populated
	with executable, debug, and oprofile sample files. This directory can be
	copied to another (host) machine and analyzed offline, with no further need to
	access the data collection machine (target).
</para>

<para>
	The following command, executed on the target system, will collect the
	sample files, the executables associated with the sample files, and the
	debuginfo files associated with the executables and copy them into
	<filename>/tmp/current_data</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
# oparchive -o /tmp/current_data
</screen>

<para>
	When transferring archived profile data to a host machine for offline analysis,
	you need to determine if the oprofile ABI format is compatible between the
	target system and the host system; if it isn't, you must run the <command>opimport</command>
	command to convert the target's sample data files to the format of your host system.
	See <xref linkend="opimport"/> for more details.
</para>

<para>
	After your profile data is transferred to the host system and (if necessary)
	you have run the <command>opimport</command> command to convert the file
	format, you can now run the <command>opreport</command> and
	<command>opannotate</command> commands.  However, you must provide an
	"archive specification" to let these post-processing tools know where to find
	of the profile data (sample files, executables, etc.); for example:
</para>

<screen>
# opreport archive:/home/user1/my_oprofile_archive --symbols
</screen>

<para>
	Furthermore, if your profile was collected on your target system into a session-dir
	other than <filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename>, the <command>oparchive</command>
	command will display a message similar to the following:
</para>

<screen>
# NOTE: The sample data in this archive is located at /home/user1/test-stuff/oprofile_data
instead of the standard location of /var/lib/oprofile.  Hence, when using opreport
and other post-processing tools on this archive, you must pass the following option:
        --session-dir=/home/user1/test-stuff/oprofile_data
</screen>

<para>
	Then the above <command>opreport</command> example would have to include that
	<option>--session-dir</option> option.
</para>

<para>
<note>
	 In some host/target development environments, all target executables, libraries, and
	 debuginfo files are stored in a root directory on the host to facilitate offline
	 analysis.  In such cases, the <command>oparchive</command> command collects more data
	 than is necessary; so, when copying the resulting output of <command>oparchive</command>,
	 you can skip all of the executables, etc, and just archive the <filename>$SESSION_DIR</filename>
	 tree located within the output directory you specified in your <command>oparchive</command>
	 command. Then, when running the <command>opreport</command> or	<command>opannotate</command>
	 commands on your host system, pass the <option>--root</option> option to point to the
	 location of your target's executables, etc.
</note>
</para>

<sect2 id="oparchive-details">
<title>Usage of <command>oparchive</command></title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--help / -? / --usage</option></term><listitem><para>
Show help message.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--exclude-dependent / -x</option></term><listitem><para>
Do not include application-specific images for libraries, kernel modules
and the kernel.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--image-path / -p [paths]</option></term><listitem><para>
Comma-separated list of additional paths to search for binaries.
This is needed to find kernel modules.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--root / -R [path]</option></term><listitem><para>
A path to a filesystem to search for additional binaries.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--output-directory / -o [directory]</option></term><listitem><para>
Output to the given directory. There is no default. This must be specified.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--list-files / -l</option></term><listitem><para>
Only list the files that would be archived, don't copy them.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--verbose / -V [options]</option></term><listitem><para>
Give verbose debugging output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--session-dir=dir_path</option></term><listitem><para>
Use sample database from the specified directory <filename>dir_path</filename> instead
of the default location. If this option is not specified, then oparchive will search for
samples in <filename>&lt;cur_dir&gt;/oprofile_data</filename>
first. If that directory does not exist, the standard session-dir of
<filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename> is used
as the session directory.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--version / -v</option></term><listitem><para>
Show version.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2> <!-- oparchive-details -->

</sect1> <!-- oparchive -->

<sect1 id="opimport">
<title>Converting sample database files (<command>opimport</command>)</title>
<para>
	This utility converts sample database files from a foreign binary format (abi) to
	the native format. This is required when moving sample files to a (host) system
	other than the one used for collection (target system), and the host and target systems are different
	architectures. The abi format of the sample files to be imported is described in a
	text file located in <filename>$SESSION_DIR/abi</filename>.  If you are unsure if
	your target and host systems have compatible architectures (in regard to the OProfile
	ABI), simply diff a <filename>$SESSION_DIR/abi</filename> file from the target system
	with one from the host system.  If any differences show up at all, you must run the
	<command>opimport</command> command.
</para>

<para>
	The <command>oparchive</command> command should be used on the machine where
	the profile was taken (target) in order to collect sample files and all other necessary
	information. The archive directory that is the output from <command>oparchive</command>
	should be copied to the system where you wish to perform your performance analysis (host).
</para>

<para>
	The following command converts an input sample file to the specified
	output sample file using the given abi file as a binary description
	of the input file and the curent platform abi as a binary description
	of the output file. (NOTE: The ellipses are used to make the example more
	compact and cannot be used in an actual command line.)
</para>

<screen>
# opimport -a /tmp/foreign-abi -o /tmp/imported/.../GLOBAL_POWER_EVENTS.200000.1.all.all.all /tmp/archived/var/lib/.../mprime/GLOBAL_POWER_EVENTS.200000.1.all.all.all
</screen>
<para>
    Since opimport converts just one file at a time, an example shell script is provided below
    that will perform an import/conversion of all sample files in a samples directory collected
    from the target system.
<screen>
#!/bin/bash
#Usage: my-import.sh &lt;foreign-abi-fullpathname&gt;

# NOTE: Start from the "samples" directory containing the "current" directory
# to be imported

mkdir current-imported
cd current-imported; (cd ../current; find . -type d ! -name .) |xargs mkdir
cd ../current; mv stats ../StatsSave; find . -type f | while read line; do opimport  -a $1 -o ../current-imported/$line $line; done; mv ../StatsSave stats;
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Example usage:  Assume that on the target system, a profile was collected using a session-dir of
<filename>/var/lib/oprofile</filename>, and then <command>oparchive -o profile1</command> was run.
Then the <filename>profile1</filename> directory is copied to the host system for analysis.  To import
the sample data in <filename>profile1</filename>, you would perform the following steps:
<screen>
$cd profile1/var/lib/oprofile/samples
$my-import.sh `pwd`/../abi
</screen>
</para>
<para>
If the OProfile ABI is truly different on host and target machines, then the end result of running the
above script will place the converted (i.e., imported) files into the <filename>current-imported</filename>
directory.  By default, <command>opreport</command> and other post-profiling tools will look for samples
in <filename>samples/current</filename> of the specified session directory.  So you should either rename
<filename>current-imported</filename> to <filename>current</filename> or specify the session specification of
<command>session:current-imported</command> when running post-profiling tools.
</para>
<para>
If the OProfile ABI is the same on the host and target machines, the <command>my-import.sh</command> script
will print the following message for each sample file:
<screen>
input abi is identical to native. no conversion necessary.
</screen>
</para>
<sect2 id="opimport-details">
<title>Usage of <command>opimport</command></title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>--help / -? / --usage</option></term><listitem><para>
Show help message.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--abi / -a [filename]</option></term><listitem><para>
Input abi file description location.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--force / -f</option></term><listitem><para>
Force conversion even if the input and output abi are identical.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--output / -o [filename]</option></term><listitem><para>
Specify the output filename. If the output file already exists, the file is
not overwritten but data are accumulated in. Sample filename are informative
for post profile tools and must be kept identical, in other word the pathname
from the first path component containing a '{' must be kept as it in the
output filename.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--verbose / -V</option></term><listitem><para>
Give verbose debugging output.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term><option>--version / -v</option></term><listitem><para>
Show version.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2> <!-- opimport-details -->

</sect1> <!-- opimport -->

</chapter>

<chapter id="interpreting">
<title>Interpreting profiling results</title>
<para>
The standard caveats of profiling apply in interpreting the results from OProfile:
profile realistic situations, profile different scenarios, profile
for as long as a time as possible, avoid system-specific artifacts, don't trust
the profile data too much. Also bear in mind the comments on the performance
counters above - you <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> rely on totally accurate
instruction-level profiling.  However, for almost all circumstances the data
can be useful. Ideally a utility such as Intel's VTUNE would be available to
allow careful instruction-level analysis; go hassle Intel for this, not me ;)
</para>
<sect1 id="irq-latency">
<title>Profiling interrupt latency</title>
<para>
This is an example of how the latency of delivery of profiling interrupts
can impact the reliability of the profiling data. This is pretty much a 
worst-case-scenario example: these problems are fairly rare.
</para>
<screen>
double fun(double a, double b, double c)
{
 double result = 0;
 for (int i = 0 ; i &lt; 10000; ++i) {
  result += a;
  result *= b;
  result /= c;
 }
 return result;
}
</screen>
<para>
Here the last instruction of the loop is very costly, and you would expect the result
reflecting that - but (cutting the instructions inside the loop):
</para>
<screen>
$ opannotate -a -t 10 ./a.out

     88 15.38% : 8048337:       fadd   %st(3),%st
     48 8.391% : 8048339:       fmul   %st(2),%st
     68 11.88% : 804833b:       fdiv   %st(1),%st
    368 64.33% : 804833d:       inc    %eax
               : 804833e:       cmp    $0x270f,%eax
               : 8048343:       jle    8048337
</screen>
<para>
The problem comes from the x86 hardware; when the counter overflows the IRQ
is asserted but the hardware has features that can delay the NMI interrupt:
x86 hardware is synchronous (i.e. cannot interrupt during an instruction);
there is also a latency when the IRQ is asserted, and the multiple
execution units and the out-of-order model of modern x86 CPUs also causes
problems. This is the same function, with annotation :
</para>
<screen>
$ opannotate -s -t 10 ./a.out

               :double fun(double a, double b, double c)
               :{ /* _Z3funddd total:     572 100.0% */
               : double result = 0;
    368 64.33% : for (int i = 0 ; i &lt; 10000; ++i) {
     88 15.38% :  result += a;
     48 8.391% :  result *= b;
     68 11.88% :  result /= c;
               : }
               : return result;
               :}
</screen>
<para>
The conclusion: don't trust samples coming at the end of a loop,
particularly if the last instruction generated by the compiler is costly. This
case can also occur for branches. Always bear in mind that samples
can be delayed by a few cycles from its real position. That's a hardware
problem and OProfile can do nothing about it.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="kernel-profiling">
<title>Kernel profiling</title>
<sect2 id="irq-masking">
<title>Interrupt masking</title>
<para>
OProfile uses non-maskable interrupts (NMI) on the P6 generation, Pentium 4,
Athlon, Opteron, Phenom, and Turion processors. These interrupts can occur even in sections of the
kernel where interrupts are disabled, allowing collection of samples in virtually
all executable code.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="idle">
<title>Idle time</title>
<para>
Your kernel is likely to support halting the processor when a CPU is idle. As
the typical hardware events like <constant>CPU_CLK_UNHALTED</constant> do not
count when the CPU is halted, the kernel profile will not reflect the actual
amount of time spent idle. You can change this behaviour by booting with
the <option>idle=poll</option> option, which uses a different idle routine. This
will appear as <function>poll_idle()</function> in your kernel profile.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="kernel-modules">
<title>Profiling kernel modules</title>
<para>
OProfile profiles kernel modules by default. However, there are a couple of problems
you may have when trying to get results. First, you may have booted via an initrd;
this means that the actual path for the module binaries cannot be determined automatically.
To get around this, you can use the <option>-p</option> option to the analysis tools
to specify where to look for the kernel modules.
</para>
<para>
In kernel version 2.6, the information on where kernel module binaries are located was removed.
This means OProfile needs guiding with the <option>-p</option> option to find your
modules. Normally, you can just use your standard module top-level directory for this.
Note that due to this problem, OProfile cannot check that the modification times match;
it is your responsibility to make sure you do not modify a binary after a profile
has been created.
</para>
<para>
If you have run <command>insmod</command> or <command>modprobe</command> to insert a module
in a particular directory, it is important that you specify this directory with the 
<option>-p</option> option first, so that it over-rides an older module binary that might
exist in other directories you've specified with <option>-p</option>. It is up to you
to make sure that these values are correct: the kernel simply does not provide enough
information for OProfile to get this information.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="interpreting-callgraph">
<title>Interpreting call-graph profiles</title>
<para>
Sometimes the results from call-graph profiles may be different from what
you expect to see. The first thing to check is whether the target
binaries where compiled with frame pointers enabled (if the binary was
compiled using <command>gcc</command>'s
<option>-fomit-frame-pointer</option> option, you will not get
meaningful results). Note that as of this writing, the GCC developers
plan to disable frame pointers by default. The Linux kernel is built
without frame pointers by default; there is a configuration option you
can use to turn it on under the "Kernel Hacking" menu.
</para>
<para>
Often you may see a caller of a function that does not actually directly
call the function you're looking at (e.g. if <function>a()</function>
calls <function>b()</function>, which in turn calls
<function>c()</function>, you may see an entry for
<function>a()->c()</function>).  What's actually occurring is that we
are taking samples at the very start (or the very end) of
<function>c()</function>; at these few instructions, we haven't yet
created the new function's frame, so it appears as if
<function>a()</function> is calling directly into
<function>c()</function>. Be careful not to be misled by these
entries.
</para>
<para>
Like the rest of OProfile, call-graph profiling uses a statistical
approach; this means that sometimes a backtrace sample is truncated, or
even partially wrong. Bear this in mind when examining results.
</para>
<!--  FIXME: what do we need here ? -->
</sect1>

<sect1 id="debug-info">
<title>Inaccuracies in annotated source</title>
<sect2 id="effect-of-optimizations">
<title>Side effects of optimizations</title>
<para>
The compiler can introduce some pitfalls in the annotated source output.
The optimizer can move pieces of code in such manner that two line of codes
are interlaced (instruction scheduling). Also debug info generated by the compiler 
can show strange behavior. This is especially true for complex expressions e.g. inside
an if statement:
</para>
<screen>
	if (a &amp;&amp; ..
	    b &amp;&amp; ..
	    c &amp;&amp;)
</screen>
<para>
here the problem come from the position of line number. The available debug
info does not give enough details for the if condition, so all samples are
accumulated at the position of the right brace of the expression. Using
<command>opannotate <option>-a</option></command> can help to show the real
samples at an assembly level.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="prologues">
<title>Prologues and epilogues</title>
<para>
The compiler generally needs to generate "glue" code across function calls, dependent
on the particular function call conventions used. Additionally other things
need to happen, like stack pointer adjustment for the local variables; this
code is known as the function prologue. Similar code is needed at function return,
and is known as the function epilogue. This will show up in annotations as
samples at the very start and end of a function, where there is no apparent
executable code in the source.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="inlined-function">
<title>Inlined functions</title>
<para>
You may see that a function is credited with a certain number of samples, but
the listing does not add up to the correct total. To pick a real example :
</para>
<screen>
               :internal_sk_buff_alloc_security(struct sk_buff *skb)
 353 2.342%    :{ /* internal_sk_buff_alloc_security total: 1882 12.48% */
               :
               :        sk_buff_security_t *sksec;
  15 0.0995%   :        int rc = 0;
               :
  10 0.06633%  :        sksec = skb-&gt;lsm_security;
 468 3.104%    :        if (sksec &amp;&amp; sksec-&gt;magic == DSI_MAGIC) {
               :                goto out;
               :        }
               :
               :        sksec = (sk_buff_security_t *) get_sk_buff_memory(skb);
   3 0.0199%   :        if (!sksec) {
  38 0.2521%   :                rc = -ENOMEM;
               :                goto out;
  10 0.06633%  :        }
               :        memset(sksec, 0, sizeof (sk_buff_security_t));
  44 0.2919%   :        sksec-&gt;magic = DSI_MAGIC;
  32 0.2123%   :        sksec-&gt;skb = skb;
  45 0.2985%   :        sksec-&gt;sid = DSI_SID_NORMAL;
  31 0.2056%   :        skb-&gt;lsm_security = sksec;
               :
               :      out:
               :
 146 0.9685%   :        return rc;
               :
  98 0.6501%   :}
</screen>
<para>
Here, the function is credited with 1,882 samples, but the annotations
below do not account for this. This is usually because of inline functions -
the compiler marks such code with debug entries for the inline function
definition, and this is where <command>opannotate</command> annotates
such samples. In the case above, <function>memset</function> is the most
likely candidate for this problem. Examining the mixed source/assembly
output can help identify such results.
</para>
<para>
This problem is more visible when there is no source file available, in the
following example it's trivially visible the sums of symbols samples is less
than the number of the samples for this file. The difference must be accounted
to inline functions.
</para>
<screen>
/*
 * Total samples for file : "arch/i386/kernel/process.c"
 *
 *    109  2.4616
 */

 /* default_idle total:     84  1.8970 */
 /* cpu_idle total:         21  0.4743 */
 /* flush_thread total:      1  0.0226 */
 /* prepare_to_copy total:   1  0.0226 */
 /* __switch_to total:      18  0.4065 */
</screen>
<para>
The missing samples are not lost, they will be credited to another source
location where the inlined function is defined. The inlined function will be
credited from multiple call site and merged in one place in the annotated
source file so there is no way to see from what call site are coming the
samples for an inlined function.
</para>
<para>
When running <command>opannotate</command>, you may get a warning
"some functions compiled without debug information may have incorrect source line attributions".
In some rare cases, OProfile is not able to verify that the derived source line
is correct (when some parts of the binary image are compiled without debugging
information). Be wary of results if this warning appears.
</para>
<para>
Furthermore, for some languages the compiler can implicitly generate functions,
such as default copy constructors. Such functions are labelled by the compiler
as having a line number of 0, which means the source annotation can be confusing.
</para>
<!-- FIXME so what *actually* happens to those samples ? ignored ? -->
</sect2>
<sect2 id="wrong-linenr-info">
<title>Inaccuracy in line number information</title>
<para>
Depending on your compiler you can fall into the following problem:
</para>
<screen>
struct big_object { int a[500]; };

int main()
{
	big_object a, b;
	for (int i = 0 ; i != 1000 * 1000; ++i)
		b = a;
	return 0;
}

</screen>
<para>
Compiled with <command>gcc</command> 3.0.4 the annotated source is clearly inaccurate:
</para>
<screen>
               :int main()
               :{  /* main total: 7871 100% */
               :        big_object a, b;
               :        for (int i = 0 ; i != 1000 * 1000; ++i)
               :                b = a;
 7871 100%     :        return 0;
               :}
</screen>
<para>
The problem here is distinct from the IRQ latency problem; the debug line number
information is not precise enough; again, looking at output of <command>opannoatate -as</command> can help.
</para>
<screen>
               :int main()
               :{
               :        big_object a, b;
               :        for (int i = 0 ; i != 1000 * 1000; ++i)
               : 80484c0:       push   %ebp
               : 80484c1:       mov    %esp,%ebp
               : 80484c3:       sub    $0xfac,%esp
               : 80484c9:       push   %edi
               : 80484ca:       push   %esi
               : 80484cb:       push   %ebx
               :                b = a;
               : 80484cc:       lea    0xfffff060(%ebp),%edx
               : 80484d2:       lea    0xfffff830(%ebp),%eax
               : 80484d8:       mov    $0xf423f,%ebx
               : 80484dd:       lea    0x0(%esi),%esi
               :        return 0;
    3 0.03811% : 80484e0:       mov    %edx,%edi
               : 80484e2:       mov    %eax,%esi
    1 0.0127%  : 80484e4:       cld
    8 0.1016%  : 80484e5:       mov    $0x1f4,%ecx
 7850 99.73%   : 80484ea:       repz movsl %ds:(%esi),%es:(%edi)
    9 0.1143%  : 80484ec:       dec    %ebx
               : 80484ed:       jns    80484e0
               : 80484ef:       xor    %eax,%eax
               : 80484f1:       pop    %ebx
               : 80484f2:       pop    %esi
               : 80484f3:       pop    %edi
               : 80484f4:       leave
               : 80484f5:       ret
</screen>
<para>
So here it's clear that copying is correctly credited with of all the samples, but the
line number information is misplaced. <command>objdump -dS</command> exposes the
same problem. Note that maintaining accurate debug information for compilers when optimizing is difficult, so this problem is not suprising.
The problem of debug information
accuracy is also dependent on the binutils version used; some BFD library versions
contain a work-around for known problems of <command>gcc</command>, some others do not. This is unfortunate but we must live with that,
since profiling is pointless when you disable optimisation (which would give better debugging entries).
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="symbol-without-debug-info">
<title>Assembly functions</title>
<para>
Often the assembler cannot generate debug information automatically.
This means that you cannot get a source report unless 
you manually define the neccessary debug information; read your assembler documentation for how you might
do that. The only
debugging info needed currently by OProfile is the line-number/filename-VMA association. When profiling assembly
without debugging info you can always get report for symbols, and optionally for VMA, through <command>opreport -l</command>
or <command>opreport -d</command>, but this works only for symbols with the right attributes.
For <command>gas</command> you can get this by
</para>
<screen>
.globl foo
	.type	foo,@function
</screen>
<para> 
whilst for <command>nasm</command> you must use
</para>
<screen>
	  GLOBAL foo:function		; [1]
</screen>
<para>
Note that OProfile does not need the global attribute, only the function attribute.
</para>
</sect1>
<!-- 

FIXME: I commented this bit out until we've written something ...

improve this ? but look first why this file is special 
<sect2 id="small-functions">
<title>Small functions</title>
<para>
Very small functions can show strange behavior. The file in your source
directory of OProfile <filename>$SRC/test-oprofile/understanding/puzzle.c</filename>
show such example
</para>
</sect2>
--> 

<sect1 id="overlapping-symbols">
	<title>Overlapping symbols in JITed code</title>
	<para>
	Some virtual machines (e.g., Java) may re-JIT a method, resulting in previously
	allocated space for a piece of compiled code to be reused. This means that, at one distinct
	code address, multiple symbols/methods may be present during the run time of the application.
	</para>
	<para>
	Since OProfile samples are buffered and don&prime;t have timing information, there is no way
	to correlate samples with the (possibly) varying address ranges in which the code for a symbol
	may reside.
	An alternative would be flushing the OProfile sampling buffer when we get an unload event,
	but this could result in high overhead.
	</para>
	<para>
	To moderate the problem of overlapping symbols, OProfile tries to select the symbol that was
	present at this address range most of the time. Additionally, other overlapping symbols
	are truncated in the overlapping area.
	This gives reasonable results, because in reality, address reuse typically takes place
	during phase changes of the application -- in particular, during application  startup.
	Thus, for optimum profiling results, start the sampling session after application startup
	and burn in.
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="interpreting_operf_results">
<title>Using operf to profile fork/execs</title>
<para>
When profiling an application that forks one or more new processes, <command>operf</command> will
record samples for both the parent process and forked processes. This is also true even if the
forked process performs an exec of some sort (e.g., <code>execvp</code>). If the
process does <emphasis>not</emphasis> perform an exec, you will see that <command>opreport</command>
will attribute samples for the forked process to the main application executable.  On the other
hand, if the forked process <emphasis>does</emphasis> perform an exec, then <command>opreport</command>
will attribute samples to the executable being exec'ed.
</para>
<para>
To demonstrate this, consider the following examples.
When using <command>operf</command> to profile a single application (either with the <code>--pid</code>
option or <code>command</code> option), the normal <command>opreport</command> summary output
(i.e., invoking <command>opreport</command> with no options) looks something like the following:
<screen>
CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
  samples|      %|
------------------
   112342 100.000 sprintft
	CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
	  samples|      %|
	------------------
	   104209 92.7605 libc-2.12.so
	     7273  6.4740 sprintft
	      858  0.7637 no-vmlinux
	        2  0.0018 ld-2.12.so
</screen>
</para>
<para>
But if you profile an application that does a fork/exec, the <command>opreport</command> summary output
will show samples for both the main application you profiled, as well as the exec'ed program.
An example is shown below where <code>s-m-fork</code> is the main application being profiled, which
in turn forks a process that does an <code>execvp</code> of the <code>memcpyt</code> program.
<screen>
CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
  samples|      %|
------------------
   133382 70.5031 memcpyt
	CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
	  samples|      %|
	------------------
	   123852 92.8551 libc-2.12.so
	     8522  6.3892 memcpyt
	     1007  0.7550 no-vmlinux
	        1 7.5e-04 ld-2.12.so
    55804 29.4969 s-m-fork
	CPU_CLK_UNHALT...|
	  samples|      %|
	------------------
	    51801 92.8267 libc-2.12.so
	     3589  6.4314 s-m-fork
	      414  0.7419 no-vmlinux
</screen>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="hidden-cost">
<title>Other discrepancies</title>
<para>
Another cause of apparent problems is the hidden cost of instructions. A very
common example is two memory reads: one from L1 cache and the other from memory:
the second memory read is likely to have more samples.
There are many other causes of hidden cost of instructions. A non-exhaustive
list: mis-predicted branch, TLB cache miss, partial register stall,
partial register dependencies, memory mismatch stall, re-executed ops. If you want to write
programs at the assembly level, be sure to take a look at the Intel and
AMD documentation at <ulink url="http://developer.intel.com/">http://developer.intel.com/</ulink>
and <ulink url="http://developer.amd.com/devguides.jsp/">http://developer.amd.com/devguides.jsp</ulink>.
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter id="controlling-counter">
<title>Controlling the event counter</title>
<sect1 id="controlling-ocount">
<title>Using <command>ocount</command></title>
<para>
This section describes in detail how <command>ocount</command> is used.
Unless the <option>--events</option> option is specified, <command>ocount</command> will use
the default event for your system. For most systems, the default event is some
cycles-based event, assuming your processor type supports hardware performance
counters. The event specification used for <command>ocount</command> is slightly
different from that required for profiling -- a <emphasis>count</emphasis> value
is not needed. You can see the event information for your CPU using <command>ophelp</command>.
More information on event specification can be found at <xref linkend="eventspec"/>.
</para>
<para>
The <command>ocount</command> command syntax is:
<para>
<screen>ocount [ options ] [ --system-wide | --process-list &lt;pids&gt; | --thread-list &lt;tids&gt; | --cpu-list &lt;cpus&gt; [ command [ args ] ] ]
</screen>
</para></para>
<para>
<command>ocount</command> has 5 run modes:
<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>system-wide</listitem>
<listitem>process-list</listitem>
<listitem>thread-list</listitem>
<listitem>cpu-list</listitem>
<listitem>command</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para></para>
<para>
One and only one of these 5 run modes must be specified when you run <command>ocount</command>.
If you run <command>ocount</command> using a run mode other than <code>command [args]</code>, press Ctrl-c
to stop it when finished counting (e.g., when the monitored process ends). If you background <command>ocount</command>
(i.e., with &amp;) while using one these run modes, you must stop it in a controlled manner so that
the data collection process can be shut down cleanly and final results can be displayed.
Use <code>kill -SIGINT &lt;ocount-PID&gt;</code> for this purpose.
</para>
<para>
Following is a description of the <command>ocount</command> options.
</para>
<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>command [args]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		The command or application to be profiled. The <emphasis>[args]</emphasis> are the input arguments
        that the command or application requires. The command and its arguments must be positioned at the
        end of the command line, after all other <command>ocount</command> options.
        </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--process-list / -p [PIDs]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Use this option to count events for one or more already-running applications, specified via
        a comma-separated list (PIDs). Event counts will be collected for all children of the
        passed process(es) as well.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--thread-list / -r [TIDs]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Use this option to count events for one or more already-running threads, specified via
        a comma-separated list (TIDs). Event counts will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be collected
        for any children of the passed thread(s).
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--system-wide / -s</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option is for counting events for all processes running on your system. You must have
        root authority to run <command>ocount</command> in this mode.
        </para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--cpu-list / -C [CPUs]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option is for counting events on a subset of processors on your system. You must have
        root authority to run <command>ocount</command> in this mode. This is a comma-separated list,
        where each element in the list may be either a single processor number or a range of processor
        numbers; for example: -C 2,3,4-11,15.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--events / -e  [event1[,event2[,...]]]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option is for passing a comma-separated list of event specifications
		for counting. Each event spec is of the form:
		</para>
		<screen>name[:unitmask[:kernel[:user]]]</screen>
		<para>
		When no event specification is given, the default event for the running
		processor type will be used for counting. Use <command>ophelp</command>
		to list the available events for your processor type.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--separate-thread / -t</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
        This option can be used in conjunction with either the <code>--process-list</code> or
        <code>--thread-list</code> option to display event counts on a per-thread (per-process) basis.
        Without this option, all counts are aggregated.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--separate-cpu / -c</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		This option can be used in conjunction with either the <code>--system-wide</code> or
		<code>--cpu-list</code> option to display event counts on a per-cpu basis. Without this option,
		all counts are aggregated.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--time-interval / -i interval_length[:num_intervals]</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Note: </command>The <code>interval_length</code> is given in milliseconds.
              However, the current implementation only supports 100 ms
              granularity, so the given <code>interval_length</code> will be rounded
              to the nearest 100 ms.  Results collected for each time
              interval are printed immediately instead of the default
              of one dump of cumulative event counts at the end of the
              run.  Counters are reset to zero at the start of each
              interval.
		</para>
		<para>
              If <code>num_intervals</code> is specified, ocount exits after the
              specified number of intervals occur.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	   <term><option>--brief-format / -b</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Use this option to print results in the following brief format:
		<para><screen>
                  [optional cpu or thread,]&lt;event_name&gt;,&lt;count&gt;,&lt;percent_time_enabled&gt;
                  [        &lt;int&gt;         ,]&lt;  string  &gt;,&lt; u64 &gt;,&lt;     double         &gt;
        </screen></para>
        If <code>--timer-interval</code> is specified, a separate line formatted as
        <para><screen>
                  timestamp,&lt;num_seconds_since_epoch&gt;[.n]
        </screen></para>
        is printed ahead of each dump of event counts. If the time interval specified is
        less than one second, the timestamp will have 1/10 second precision.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>

	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--output-file / -f outfile_name</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Results are written to outfile_name instead of interactively to the terminal.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--verbose / -V</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Use this option to increase the verbosity of the output.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--version -v </option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Show <command>ocount</command> version.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term><option>--help / -h</option></term>
		<listitem><para>
		Show a help message.
		</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter id="ack">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>
Thanks to (in no particular order) : Arjan van de Ven, Rik van Riel, Juan Quintela, Philippe Elie,
Phillipp Rumpf, Tigran Aivazian, Alex Brown, Alisdair Rawsthorne, Bob Montgomery, Ray Bryant, H.J. Lu,
Jeff Esper, Will Cohen, Graydon Hoare, Cliff Woolley, Alex Tsariounov, Al Stone, Jason Yeh,
Randolph Chung, Anton Blanchard, Richard Henderson, Andries Brouwer, Bryan Rittmeyer,
Maynard P. Johnson,
Richard Reich (rreich@rdrtech.com), Zwane Mwaikambo, Dave Jones, Charles Filtness; and finally Pulp, for "Intro".
</para>
</chapter>

</book>
